I humbly request that Your Highness
儿臣拜请母后
mete out justice to Zhang Xingwei
按律处置张行微
but I also
但
implore you to consider his past merits
张氏家族族人
and show leniency to
还望母后念及过往功绩
the members of the Zhang Family.
从轻发落
Your Royal Highness,
太皇太后
The members of the Zhangs have served
张氏一族
as Prime Minister for three generations,
三代为相
contributing to the stability of the realm.
于大苍社稷有功
Lord Zhang's mistake should not implicate
一人过错
the innocent members of the entire family.
何至牵连全族无辜族人
Lord Shen,
沈卿
is this really what you wish for?
你真是这么想的
I understand the pain of being imprisoned.
沈某自知入罪容所之苦
I only wish
臣只愿
for the truth to be revealed.
真相大白
In the eighth year of the Shengli era,
大苍圣历八年
Prime Minister Zhang Xingwei was
宰相张行微
given poisoned wine and took his own life.
被赐毒酒自尽
Prince Xian volunteered to guard the borders,
贤王萧重自请镇守边疆
and would not return for a decade.
十年不还
The Jinxiufang Workshop case has been overturned.
锦绣坊案平反洗冤
Shen Bingzhu's treason case was retried.
沈秉烛通敌一案获重审
The Zhou Family's implicated officials
周氏涉事官员
have been sentenced,
皆被治罪
with their kins
周氏亲眷
exiled for life
贬回原籍
from Xiang'an.
终生不得再入襄安
The Shen Family's name has been cleared.
沈家终沉冤昭雪
Father,
父亲
mother,
母亲
I did it.
孩儿做到了
By the will of God,
应天顺时
we hereby declare:
受兹明命
Lord Shen Bingzhu
昔日沈侍郎沈秉烛
was wrongfully accused of treason.
通敌一案
It was indeed a miscarriage of justice.
实为冤案
Shen Du's loyalty is evident to all.
沈家二世忠良天地可鉴
He's hereby awarded the medal for gallantry.
现今特赐忠勇碑
The implicated will be reinterred with full honors.
沈府旧人移棺厚葬
Their family will receive special privileges.
相关家眷老小一律优待
Uncle Shen,
沈伯伯
are you seeing this?
你看到了吗
He has proven the Shen Family's innocence.
为沈家伸冤
He has succeeded.
他做到了
So clever.
聪明
Good boy.
乖
Mother,
母后
I've recognized my mistakes.
儿臣知错
I humbly request punishment.
恳请母后治儿臣的罪
If I intend to punish you,
要治你的罪
do I have to wait until now?
我还等到今日啊
Yongan,
永安
I will not punish you, and it's not merely
我不治你的罪
because of our mother-daughter bond,
不是因为我们母女之情
but because you only
只是因为
provided support to the local garrisons,
你只捐助了地方军士
which neither harms the empire
于大苍无碍
nor threatens the monarch.
于社稷无忧
If you had
但凡
even a hint of treasonous intent...
你有一丝谋反之心
I would never dare to.
儿臣万万不敢
I have donated all my personal wealth
儿臣已经将全部的私产
to the treasury,
纳入国库
and my fate is
身家性命
in Your Royal Highness' hands.
也任由母后做主
You may rise.
起来吧
Such a mistake
此事
must be avoided in the future.
再不可犯
This lesson is etched in my heart.
儿臣谨记于心
Yongan,
永安
do you think you could
你以为
secure the support from the provinces
给地方上一些
by providing them
军备钱财
with arms and funds?
就得民心了
True loyalty
所谓民心
cannot be bought.
是收买不来的
With your brother guarding the frontier,
如今你皇弟镇守边疆
isn't it time for you
你在襄安
to contribute to the empire
是否应该为大苍
from Xiang'an?
做点什么事了
I shouldn't have to remind you, right?
不用我再跟你说了吧
I will dedicate myself wholeheartedly
儿臣定当竭尽全力
to supporting His Majesty.
全心全意辅佐圣上
That's good.
明白就好
As the saying goes.
正所谓
A regime prospers
政之所兴
by following the desires of its citizens,
在顺民意
and it collapses by
政之所废
going against their hearts.
在逆民心
The people hate hardship and toil;
民恶忧劳
I will bring them ease and joy.
我佚乐之
The people loathe poverty;
民恶贫贱
I will bring them wealth and honor.
我富贵之
Keep going, my dear!
你说 说
The people fear danger;
民恶危坠
I will ensure their safety and stability.
我存安之
The people dread extinction;
民恶灭绝
I will nourish them to make them thrive.
我生育之
Won... wonderful!
好 好 好啊
Qi has finally spoken!
麒儿终于开口说话了
Qi!
麒儿
His Majesty has grown up!
圣上长大了
He has truly grown up!
长大了
He can talk now!
说话了
He has finally spoken!
开口说话了
Auntie!
姑母
Look, look!
你快来 你快来
His Majesty has spoken!
圣上开口了
Runing.
汝宁
Greetings, Your Royal Highness.
参见太皇太后
Come on, get up, up!
快快起来 快快起来
This is a family gathering,
我们是家庭聚会
no need for formalities!
无须多礼
I have received the lily sachet
太皇太后送的百合香囊
from Your Highness.
我收下了
But I
只是
prefer the night-blooming jasmine sachet.
我更喜欢夜来香的香囊
Runing,
汝宁
your choice not to give back the present
你此次不退礼
is a gesture of honor to me.
是给我面子呀
I'll keep it in mind, and I'll
我记下了
send you a night-blooming jasmine sachet.
送你夜来香的香囊
By the will of God,
应天顺时
we hereby declare: I've heard that
受兹明命
Yan Xing, Chief Clerk of the Ministry of Justice,
朕闻刑部都官主事颜幸
is both virtuous and talented,
德才兼备
and has solved many challenging cases.
屡破奇案
I hereby promote her to the position of minister,
特擢升刑部主事
and I bestow upon her
赐朕亲笔书写之
a plaque inscribed in my own hand,
神探匾额
to honor her contributions.
以显其功
By royal decree.
钦
I'm grateful for His Majesty's grace.
谢圣上隆恩
Lady Yan, please rise.
颜主事快快请起
We came to deliver the imperial decree,
我等传旨啊
but we circled Xiang'an City
可是绕着襄安城
for a while.
好一会儿
Initially, we went to the Shen residence,
起先是到了沈府
but unexpectedly,
不想主事
you were visiting the Yans.
竟是在娘家访亲呢
Gratitude, my lord.
有劳大人了
Hot tea has been prepared for you.
内室已备好热茶
Please come in!
大人快请进
I must return to the palace,
还得急着回宫复命
so I won't disturb you any further.
就不叨扰了
Gratitude, my lord.
有劳大人了
Please.
大人请
Xing,
六娘
you are remarkable!
有本事啊
Is there any increase in your salary?
加俸禄不
This is an honor to the family.
光耀门楣
Truly an honor!
光耀门楣啊
This is the first plaque personally
这可是圣上临政以来
inscribed by His Majesty
亲笔书写的
since he ascended the throne!
第一块匾额啊
Is that so?
真的
When I've reached the end of my days,
我颜阔百年之后
I, Yan Kuo, will have the honor to meet
也有面目能见
the ancestors of our Yan Family.
咱们颜府的列祖列宗了
Father,
爹
why are you saying such things
好端端的
when everything seems fine?
说这种话干吗
Even though I wish
虽说爹爹很想
to keep this plaque in the Yan residence,
将这匾额一直留在颜府
but in a few days,
但是过几日
you should still take it
你还是将这匾额
back to the Shen residence.
带回沈府去
Now that you are married,
这既已嫁为人妇
what decorum is there in lingering here?
老待在娘家成何体统啊
Father,
爹
I have already divorced Shen Du.
我与沈渡已经和离
What reason do I have to return there?
哪来回沈府的道理
Is it possible that father
父亲难不成
wishes to expel me?
是想赶我出府
Look,
你看
how could I possibly mean that?
我怎么能有这个意思呢
Couples fight,
小两口吵架嘛
but they always find a way to reconcile.
床头吵架床尾和
It's not beneficial to remain
你说你这一直僵着
stuck in this stalemate,
它也不是个事啊
don't you agree?
对不对
Hey,
你看
well,
这
After the promotion,
这当了主事之后
her temper has grown even worse.
这脾气还大了还
My lord, my lord!
大人大人
Congratulations, my lord!
恭喜大人
Best wishes, my lord!
贺喜大人
Your salary has increased by ten percent!
这俸禄又加一成
That doesn't really matter.
加不加的无所谓
Yeah, yeah.
对对对
Wealth is but a fleeting possession.
身外之物
As an official, I, Wu Taiming,
我吴泰明为官
do not seek fame or fortune.
不为名 不为利
My aspiration lies
为的是
in cultivating myself,
修身
leading my family with honor, and
齐家
contributing to the welfare of the state.
治国的理想
Right, right,
是是是
you are absolutely right, my lord.
大人您说得是
However, let's not forget,
但是话说回来
your award is
您这次受赏
a recognition of
那也是因为当初
your noble character,
大人您的高义啊
right?
是不是
you see,
您看看
think back to when
当初 对吧
Lord Shen
大阁领
and Lady Yan
颜主事
were in grave danger.
深陷危难之际啊
Everyone else shied away,
所有旁人避之不及啊
but you, my lord, you
唯有大人您
stepped forward without hesitation.
挺身而出
You faced the danger head-on to help them!
他两肋插刀啊
I, Feng Gui, am
我冯贵真是
utterly in awe of you,
佩服得五体投地
in awe of you!
五体投地
My lord...
大人
Feng boy,
小小冯啊
do you know the reason behind my act?
你可知道这是为什么
I don't know.
不知道
I've served as an official for two decades,
老夫我为官二十年
and the most valuable lesson I've learned
最宝贵的经验
is...
就是
What is it?
什么
Please enlighten me!
您说您说
Cooking on new stoves!(Align with those who have potential.)
烧冷灶
About new stoves,
这冷灶
how to nurture the flames,
怎么烧
when to light the new stoves;
何时烧
it's actually an art.
那可都是学问
Cooking on new stoves?
烧冷灶
Feng boy...
小小冯
Qi Yeyun, the new constable,
刑部捕快齐野云
reporting for duty.
前来报到
Yeyun?
野云
Yes, I am.
对
I am Feng Gui,
鄙人是
the squad leader of the constables.
督捕司班头冯贵
Come, come, everyone,
来来来 所有人
put down your work.
把手里活都放下
Come on, gather around,
快快快 过来过来
let's welcome the new guy!
见人了
Hurry up!
快点
Come on.
快快快
Come on, double time!
快点快点 麻利点
I, er...
我呢
We're delighted to
我们大家
welcome you to
特别热烈地欢迎你
join our family at
加入我们
the Constables' Office.
督捕司的大家庭
Welcome aboard!
欢迎欢迎欢迎
Cooking on a new stove, huh?
烧冷灶啊
Alright, alright, get to work.
行行 忙去吧
Qi Yeyun
这齐野云
already calls Lord Shen brother-in-law,
都喊沈大阁领姐夫了
so he's definitely an old stove.
那妥妥的热灶
What's there to cook over there?
烧个屁啊
You still have a lot to learn!
且学呢
This is good.
好啊
Feels good, huh, father?
舒服吗 爹
Absolutely!
舒服
Is there any way I wouldn't enjoy
我女儿给我捶背
my daughter's massage?
能不舒服吗
Father,
爹
this worker is giving it his all,
怎么样
wouldn't you say?
这长工卖力吧
He certainly works hard.
当然卖力了
This is commendable.
卖力好啊
Sweetie,
女儿
our pawnshop has been
你说咱们家这个当铺
losing workers one after another.
招一个伙计走一个
It's a never-ending cycle.
招一个走一个
Thankfully,
这次
I have a diligent and hardworking
幸亏有这么一个
son-in-law now.
勤谨肯干的女婿
Langxing,
郎行
come, sit down and take a break;
来 坐着歇会儿
enjoy a cup of tea with us.
喝口茶
I've fine.
没事
I have plenty of energy,
我有得是力气
so I'm not tired at all.
我不累
Langxing,
郎行
I think you could really use
我看你啊
a set of armor that's made of gold!
缺一套黄金甲
How about this,
这么着
I'll order a set for you!
我给你订一套
No, really, I'm OK.
不 不用
You already gifted me
您上次已经给了我
a hat of gold last time.
一个金帽子了
It's really not necessary.
我真不用
Don't say no.
别推辞
Let me tell you,
我告诉你啊
An armor made of gold
黄金甲呀
would suit you perfectly!
你最配
Oh... this...
这 这
It's far too extravagant!
太 太贵重了
I truly can't accept such a gift.
我真不能收
Are you taking it or not?
你要不要
Yes, I will...
要
That's more like it.
对嘛
Don't refuse Father's gift!
我爹给你就接着嘛
What she said makes perfect sense,
我女儿说得对
gifts from the elders
长辈送的东西
should never be turned down.
不能推辞
Exactly.
就是
Yes,
是
I... I'll return to work now...
我 我继续忙去了
Your Royal Highness,
太皇太后
the renovation of the Ming Hall
明堂的重建修缮工作
has been successfully completed.
已经完成
The composition by Mr. Jin for the
金乐师为明堂重建
Ming Hall is close to completion,
所作曲谱
with only the ending left to finish.
只余结尾便可完谱
I have asked the palace musicians
臣已请宫中乐师
to complete the last part of the melody.
接着谱完最后一段旋律
I pray it brings Your Highness pleasure.
请太皇太后鉴赏
Wonderful!
好
I feel completely reassured with you
沈爱卿办事
overseeing things, Lord Shen.
哀家最为放心
This piece still lacks a title.
此曲还差曲名未取
I humbly request
沈某不才
Your Highness to bestow a title upon it.
请太皇太后赐名
With all things prepared
万物备俱
for everlasting happiness,
长乐无忧
let's call it the "Melody of Golden Age!"
就叫长乐曲
I envision that on the day
哀家想啊
the Ming Hall reopens,
等明堂重开之日
I'd like to invite the people of Xiang'an
我想邀请襄安的百姓
to come in and visit,
入内参观
to share in the joy
共享其乐
and appreciate the
共赏
"Melody Of Golden Age!"
长乐曲
Lord Shen,
大阁领
my lady mentioned that,
六姑娘说
now that you've divorced,
既已和离
it's best not to disturb her.
劝君勿扰
I humbly request you to leave now.
大阁领还是请回吧
Farewell.
告辞
Lord Shen,
大阁领
this marks the ninth time
这已经是你
you've been turned away.
被退礼的第九次了
I think...
我觉得吧
I think
我觉得
the gift isn't impressive enough,
是这次礼物不够好
not heartfelt enough.
不够打动人
Xing,
六娘
he's already visited nine times.
这都上门第九次了
He is genuinely sincere.
大阁领可是很有诚意了
Don't hold a grudge against him.
你就别跟他置气了
Just go home with him.
跟他回家吧
That's right, Xing,
是啊 六娘
a respectable commander
人家堂堂大阁领
stands at our gate all day,
整天在咱们门口趴着
and this doesn't
这人来过往的
reflect well on us.
也不好看啊
You should show your husband some respect.
你就给你夫君点面子
Mother,
娘
sister,
三姐
why are you all
你们怎么
defending him?
都帮着他说话呀
He's the one who insisted on the divorce.
是他自说自话要和离的
I'm merely honoring his choice.
我只是成全他而已
Besides,
再说了
I never asked him
我又没有让他
to linger at our door all day.
整天在家门口蹲着
Hey, where are you going?
不是 你干吗去
Food!
吃饭
I'm hungry, mother.
饿了 阿娘
I'll go prepare some food for you.
那我给你做饭去
Easy, you!
你慢着点
Be careful with your child!
当心肚子
Jing Lin, let's go
景林
change the betrothal gifts again.
我们再去买
Is that for real?
真有此事
Word has traveled across Xiang'an City.
襄安城都传遍了
Lord Shen has been rejected nine times.
沈大阁领被退礼了九回
And he's eagerly going to
还巴巴地去请新娘子
propose to Xing for the tenth time!
第十次呢
It's just hilarious!
真是太好笑了
Isn't that Lord Shen over there?
这不是沈大阁领吗
He should be called "White Gift (in vain)"
如今白无常
instead of "The White Death!"
应该叫白送礼了
Will this tenth attempt succeed?
这第十次追妻能成功吗
They seem to have bought quite some gifts,
看他们买了不少礼物
and they look quite lavish.
还挺贵的
-This time it should work, right? -My lord.
这次应该妥了吧 大阁领
I have purchased the trendiest earrings
最新的耳饰簪子
and hairpins, each in a complete set.
都各买了一套
You carry them.
你拿着
I...
我
I really can't carry all of this!
我真拎不下了
Why didn't you ask more
您为何不多找两个人
people to come and help?
来拎呢
The Imperial Guard has plenty of manpower.
咱们内卫府又不缺人
What do you know?
你懂什么呀
The less known, the better.
此事越少人知道越好
Is there a single soul in Xiang'an
这整个襄安城
who hasn't heard?
还有人不知道吗
No one knows, no one knows...
不知道不知道
We support you, Lord Shen!
我们支持你大阁领
May you soon embrace your beloved!
早日抱得美人归
No one knows, no one knows...
不知道不知道
You have our blessing!
我们支持你
Lord Shen, go for it!
大阁领  我们支持你
Well,
也好
all the young men in Xiang'an City
全襄安城的郎君啊
should take him as a cautionary example!
都要以他为戒
It's imperative they learn
得告诉他们
not to displease their wives!
万万不可得罪娘子
Your Royal Highness,
禀太皇太后
Lady Yan has arrived.
颜主事到了
Let her in.
请她进来
Yes.
是
She's here.
来了
Greetings, Your Royal Highness.
颜幸见过太皇太后
You may rise.
起来说话
Come closer.
来
Let's chat.
近前说话
I summoned you here for two reasons.
今日召你进宫
First,
一则
the festival season has arrived.
是正逢佳节
And both I and Lady Xu
哀家和徐内司
would like to catch up with you.
都想和你叙叙家常
Secondly,
二则呀
I have some good news to share.
有个好消息要告诉你
Her Royal Highness has issued a decree
太皇太后已下懿旨
to change the method
着令
of selecting officials
改门荫取仕
from "inheritance" to "merit-based."
为择贤取仕
From now on, regardless the background,
日后不论出身
everyone will have a fair opportunity
人人都有公平机会
to pursue their goals
求取功名
and serve the empire.
为国效力
All the students from humble backgrounds
全天下寒门学子
will surely appreciate Your Highness'
必会感念
recognition of their talents and
太皇太后惜才之心
study diligently to serve the empire.
刻苦学习以报国
You may enter.
过去吧
Next.
下一个
Lift your arms.
抬手
Enter.
过去吧
Turn around.
转身
Good.
好
Pan Chi!
潘驰
It's really you!
果然是你啊
What?
怎么了
Can't I take the exam?
我就不能考试了
Of course you can!
当然可以了
We welcome candidates from
我们这里啊
all over the empire to take the exam.
欢迎全天下的考生来考
How come I heard that
只是我怎么听说
someone
有一个人
isn't interested in becoming an official?
他对做官不感兴趣啊
One becomes red by being close to red (Pig),
真是近朱者赤
and black by being close to ink!
近墨者黑啊
The way you're speaking now
你现在这说话的语气
is increasingly resembling Lu Chuichui.
和陆垂垂是越来越像了
Are you implying that Chui is ink?
你说垂垂她是墨
I'm saying she's the pig (red).
我说的猪自然是她
You!
你
I'm not interested in being an official.
我对做官没兴趣
I simply need to use
我只是势必要用
this exam to prove myself
这场考试证明自己
and also to see if
顺便检验一下
your exam
你们这考试
is genuinely fair.
是否真的公平
Alright,
好
Then make sure to take the exam seriously
那你就好好考试
and evaluate it thoroughly.
认真检验
There are certain things
有些事情
I have long wished to do.
哀家早就想做了
It's just that for a long time,
就是长久以来
I haven't found the right moment.
不便去做
In my heart,
哀家心里
I have never forgotten Chen Baiyi.
从未忘记过陈白衣啊
Yan Xing speaks on behalf of Chen Baiyi
颜幸代陈白衣
and the students from humble backgrounds
代寒门学子
to express their gratitude to Your Highness.
谢过太皇太后
Lady Yan,
颜主事
you always think of others,
你这总为他人着想
but it's important to
有空
prioritize your own needs as well.
也该多想想自己的事
Me?
我
What needs might that be?
我什么事啊
Look, I'm
你看
providing opportunities for the students.
哀家给学子们应考机会
What about you?
那你呢
Shouldn't you also
你是不是
give those around you
也该给身边人
a chance to retake the exam?
一次重考的机会啊
As the saying goes,
有道是
"better to cherish the one who is near."
不如怜取眼前人
Wakey, wakey.
起来起来
Mother is here for you.
阿娘来找你了
Mother.
阿娘
Why are you waking me up so early?
大清早的拉我起来干吗
Today is my day off.
今天可是我的休沐日
Get up and get dressed,
起来更衣
or the ceremony will be delayed.
不然仪式就要晚了
What ceremony?
什么仪式
Everyone, come in,
都进来
and set everything down properly.
把东西放好了
Be careful!
当心点
Yes, my lady.
是 是
Caiwei, easy.
三娘你慢着点啊
Everything is ready.
东西都放好了
Put this over there.
这放那儿
Yes.
是
Be quick.
手脚利索点
Easy, don't break anything.
慢点 别磕了碰了
Be careful, place it gently.
小心啊 轻放
Mother!
阿娘
What's going on?
这是在干吗
Here's the thing,
是这样啊
I went to the ancestral hall
你阿娘我
to consult our ancestors,
去祠堂问了祖宗
and then went to see a fortune teller.
又去庙里找了神婆
They all said that you,
他们都说你啊
having entered into a marriage
此前不明不白地
without proper rites,
结了一个没有行礼的婚
and then inexplicably
后来又莫名其妙地
going through a divorce.
要和离
You have committed a great disrespect,
此是犯了大不敬
and violated a serious taboo.
犯了大忌
You have deceived our ancestors,
既骗了祖宗
and also deceived God.
又骗了月老
In the future,
将来啊
you will face calamities!
会有劫难
Mother!
阿娘
So you are saying that
那你的意思是
even God doesn't allow me to divorce?
神仙都不准我和离
No, no.
不是不是不是
I've thought it through,
你阿娘我都想通了
If you want a divorce, then fine!
你想要和离那就离
But to break this calamity,
但此劫得破
the only way is to
破解之法唯有
go through the wedding ceremony
将婚礼仪式
seriously once again.
都先认认真真走一遍
After registering with God,
在神仙那边挂个号之后
then you can get a proper divorce!
再正经八百和离
Right, Xing,
是啊 六娘
I've also consulted the fortune teller.
我也问过神婆了
This calamity is not only bad for you,
此劫不光对你不好
but also for our Yan Family.
也对我们颜家不好
I'm a bit scared too.
我也是有点害怕
Yeah, Xing,
是啊 六娘
look,
你看
Caiwei is still pregnant.
三姐还怀着孩子呢
It's safer to
这事
trust this than
宁可信其有
to question it.
不可信其无
To find happiness in life,
人总是要跟
one must be with their beloved,
相爱的人在一起
treating each other
相敬如宾
with respect and
彼此珍视
cherishing one another.
这一辈子才能幸福啊
From now on,
从今往后
you will no longer be alone.
你不会再是一个人
I will definitely strive
我一定会努力
to help you uncover the truth.
帮你找出真相
This virtuous lady is
这位贤德淑女
none other than me!
就是我
Seducing me?
就凭你
I'm out of your league.
也想挑逗我
Snatch the bride?
抢亲
Can it really work?
真的能行吗
Of course.
能行
What are you doing?
行什么礼啊
The wedding is about to start!
都要结婚了
Who said he wanted to hold a
是谁说要为我好姐妹
sincere wedding
补办一场
for my best friend?
诚意满满的大婚啊
Having second thoughts?
反悔了
Of course not.
当然不是
I fear that I might get scolded by my wife
这不是怕先斩后奏
for acting without permission...
被夫人骂吗
Why are you even more rigid
你怎么比江古板
than my poker face?
还古板啊
What's there to fear about being scolded?
被骂怕什么
You should worry that she might ignore you.
怕的是娘子不理你
Lord Shen,
大阁领
when it comes to getting married,
娶妻之事
you should have the courage
就应该拿出视死如归
to risk everything and
不达目的不罢休的
not give up until you succeed.
勇气才行
Lord Shen,
大阁领
congratulations,
恭喜大阁领
my wife mentioned,
我娘子说了
although Xing is reluctant,
六妹妹虽不情不愿
she still sat down to prepare herself.
但还是坐下来梳妆了
Lord Shen,
大阁领
don't you see?
这您还不明白吗
My lady is
夫人她是
incredibly clever.
何等聪明的人啊
How could she not realize
她能看不出来
that this is all a setup?
今日是个套
Since she's willing to prepare herself,
既然能坐下来梳妆
it clearly shows that in her heart,
说明她心里面
she must be willing to do it.
肯定是愿意的
Exactly.
就是
The dignified Lord Shen
堂堂大阁领
is not as quick-witted
还不如人景内卫
as your subordinate.
一点就通
Lord Shen,
大阁领
charge!
进攻吧
Let's go!
走
My love,
六娘
I have come to take you home!
夫君我来娶你回家了
Alright,
好了
let me see.
快看看
So gorgeous!
真好看
Truly worthy of being my daughter,
真不愧是我的女儿
so radiant!
真水灵
Like a flower, like jade,
真是如花似玉
I just can't get enough of you!
真看不够
She looks just like me!
太像我了
Mother!
娘
Please...
你真是的
Ladies and gentlemen,
几位
have you figured out
这第一关的灯谜谜底
the answer to the riddle?
可曾猜出来
"A line of white egrets flying in the sky."
一行白鹭上青天
Congratulations,
恭喜
you got the last riddle correctly.
最后一道谜题猜对了
Fortunately, I, Lu Chuichui, is here,
还好有我陆垂垂
otherwise, with you muscle-heads,
不然靠你们几个木头
we wouldn't finish before dark.
天黑都猜不完
Yes, yes.
是是是
You're absolutely right.
我们垂垂说得对
Our Yan Family is a scholarly family.
我们颜家乃书香门第
If one wishes to marry
想要娶
a lady from our family,
我们颜家的女子为妻
they must possess exceptional talent.
得才情出众才是
Now, for the next round,
这下一关
you must compose a poem
须作好诗
to express your affection.
表衷情
It seems that Lord Shen has
看来沈大阁领
advanced to the second round.
闯到第二关了
Caiwei's poetry exam
三姐考作诗
is not an easy hurdle to overcome.
可不是那么容易过的
Sick with wine before flowers,
日日花前长病酒
I don't avoid the mirror's fading face.
不辞镜里朱颜瘦
From dawn to dusk, watching the clouds.
晓看天色暮看云
Whether walking or sitting,
行也思幸
I think of you! (Xing).
坐也思幸
Alone on a bridge, the wind fills my sleeves.
独立小桥风满袖
In the quiet woods, the moon appears.
平林新月人归后
Who can share the joys of life with me?
赏心乐事共谁论
Fortunately, I have met you,
幸得识卿
so I (Du) can return home!
渡可归矣
Thank you for your timely rescue.
谢谢你及时赶到
Your ears are all red from the cold.
耳朵都冻红了
What are you doing?
你要干吗
I just want everyone to see
我就是要让人家看到
that we have a harmonious marriage.
坐实我们夫妻和睦
Xing girl,
六娘啊
I think you should just step outside.
我看要不你就出去吧
The poems he made
沈大阁领作的这些歪诗
are so awful,
酸得我连豆腐
they could make me nauseous.
都咬不动了
Yeah, Xing,
是啊 六娘
just stop him.
你就别让他念了
We're all at this age,
我们都这般年纪了
so we can't handle the torment!
可禁不起折腾啊
Good poems,
好诗
with brilliant literary talent,
文采斐然
you've passed the second round!
这第二关过了
Please, my lord.
请吧 大阁领
The last round
这最后一关
is a martial arts competition.
是比武
If you want to marry my sister,
要想娶我妹妹
fine!
可以
But first, you have to defeat both of us.
不过先得打赢我们俩
Or, you can forget about taking sis.
不然休想带走我姐姐
My lord,
大阁领
you've got this round secured.
这关稳了
-Don't move! -What's this for?
别动啊 干什么
My lord, hurry and go!
大阁领快走
This is completely unfair.
这完全就是在作弊
Asking Mojie and
让五哥
a lad to take on him,
和一个小孩去比武
is this even a challenge?
这算关卡吗
How about I compete with him in dancing?
那娘跟他比舞
You lost!
你输了
What?
什么
They...
他们
defeated Shen Du?
能赢沈渡
I think he was deliberately losing.
我看他就是故意输的
Oh no, Xing,
坏了 六娘
Shen Du lost,
那沈渡输了
and he is leaving in a huff
丧气地带着
with the wedding procession!
迎亲队伍走了
Shen Du,
沈渡
you are still here?
你没走啊
My love, you are here,
夫人在这儿
where could I possibly be?
为夫能去哪儿啊
Well done, Shen Du,
好你个沈渡
putting on such a grand act to deceive me!
做这么一大场戏骗我
I...
我
I'm foolish,
为夫愚钝
unable to win over such a clever wife.
哄不好如此聪明的夫人
So I could only put on a show.
所以只能做戏作假
You won't hold it against me, will you?
夫人不会怪我吧
This shall not be repeated.
下不为例
May you have a son soon!
早生贵子
Wishing you a century of harmony!
百年好合
My love,
夫人
shall we go home?
我们回家好不好
Let's go home!
回家咯